<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2015, v.4002--><description xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" appl="X06|X07|X10|X24|X29|X33|X35|X38|X40|X43|X44|X45|X47|X48|X52|X53|X54|X56|X57|X61|X62|X63|X64|X65|X66|X67|X70|X73|X74|X76|X77|X79|X81|X82|X83|X84|X85|X87|X90|X91|X92|X94|X95|X98|XFC|XFE|XRQ|XTP|XFB|XFD|XZH|XHA|XZG|XFA|XZJ|X55|XEF|XJD|XBA|XBB|XJA|XBC|XJC|XJE|XBG|XJB|XJK|XJF|XFK|XHN|XJL|XCB|X27|X58|XDD|X59|X17|X41|X42|X09|X75|XAV|XJ1|XFF|XJH|X1310|XDE|X1316|XR210|X1317|XR310|X1322|X1318|XZ110|X1312" id="RDE-000316390" xml:lang="en" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:ptc:names:renault:dita:xsd:description.xsd"><title translate="no">bodywork component straightening : description</title><descprolog translate="no"><status name="Published" translate="no"/><critdates translate="no"><created date="04/11/21 06:28" translate="no"/><revised modified="10/10/24 13:40" translate="no"/></critdates><descmetadata translate="no"><siename translate="no">bodywork component straightening : description</siename><sieversion translate="no">N.1</sieversion><sietype translate="yes">Description</sietype><sienumber translate="no">RDE-000316390</sienumber><domain translate="no">MR</domain><company translate="no">RENAULT</company></descmetadata></descprolog><description id="d1e112" translate="no"><title translate="yes">removing dents from steel components</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">Used only for straightening visible external components:</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">rear wing panels,</li><li translate="yes">door panels,</li><li translate="yes">side panels,</li><li translate="yes">lining components without a primary structural function (e.g.: wheel arches, floor).</li></ul><para translate="yes">It does not require heavy straightening equipment and can be performed anywhere in the bodyshop.</para><para translate="yes">For all dent removal or heating operations, always start at the outside of the deformity and work towards the centre.</para></descbody><description id="d1e131" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Dent removal with access via the internal face</title><description id="d1e135" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Straightening</title><descbody translate="no"><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-5-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-2" translate="no"><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000027795_LAY-000077048.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-5-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-2-000027795</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">Straighten the internal face using a drift, stake or hammer until as close as possible to the required shape, then use a planishing hammer or mallet and a suitable stake to strike "the opposite way" .</para></descsection></descbody></description><description id="d1e149" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Heating</title><descbody translate="no"><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-3-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-3" translate="no"><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000027793_LAY-000077049.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-3-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-3-000027793</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">The operation is performed using an oxyacetylene torch, a flat stake and a mallet.</para><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">For steel, this operation destroys all original anti-corrosion protection on the internal and external faces of the heated zones. It is essential to carry out a painting procedure on the internal faces.</para></noteR></descsection></descbody></description><description id="d1e165" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Shape finishing</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">By definition, shape finishing on a zone accessible via the internal face must be by "planishing" and heating. Under no circumstances should the component panel be filed or ground, so as not to reduce its thickness.</para></descbody></description></description><description id="d1e174" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Dent removal without access via internal face</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">This type of straightening is performed with a "welding/puller" type tool, using two techniques depending on the force to be applied.</para></descbody><description id="d1e183" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Single point inertia straightening</title><descbody translate="no"><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">During an operation of this type on the B-pillar, disconnect the side airbags inertia switch electrical connector.</para></noteR><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-6-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-4" translate="no"><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000027796_LAY-000077050.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-6-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-4-000027796</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">Steel :</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">the operation consists of repeatedly welding a star shape into the recesses of the dent. This is fixed at the end of a rod, along which an inertia weight slides.</li></ul></descsection><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">Always start the repair from the outside edge and work inwards, finishing at the centre.</para></noteR><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-7-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-5" translate="no"><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000027797_LAY-000077051.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-7-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-5-000027797</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">Aluminium :</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">this requires a specific technique and equipment, consisting of welding a threaded stud onto which the pulling device is screwed.</li></ul></descsection><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-2-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-6" translate="no"><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000029444_LAY-000077052.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-2-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-6-000029444</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">When the operation is complete, the stud is cut then ground. Do not under any circumstances reduce the thickness of the panel, to avoid weakening the component.</para></descsection></descbody></description><description id="d1e228" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Straightening by multipoint pulling</title><descbody translate="no"><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-9-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-8" translate="no"><image dimension="F1 (85x60) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000025381_LAY-000077054.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 60.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-9-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-8-000025381</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">This technique is used for straightening deep gouge marks; it consists of welding a series of parallel rings in the recess of the deformity, into which a rod is fitted to allow a lever system equipped with a "clamp" to be attached. The advantage is that it can be used to straighten a significant deformation with a single pull.</para></descsection></descbody></description><description id="d1e242" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Heating</title><descbody translate="no"><descsection translate="no"><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">For steel, this operation destroys all original anti-corrosion protection on the internal and external faces of the heated zones. It is essential to inject wax into the hollow sections to protect the internal faces.</para></noteR><para translate="yes">Steel :</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">an inductor type tool may be used, however in this process the metal is only hardened on the surface to avoid blistering; lengthening of the panel cannot be reduced.</li></ul><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">In the event of excessive lengthening of the panel without access to the internal face, the component must be replaced.</para></noteR></descsection></descbody></description><description id="d1e265" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Shape finishing</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">In accordance with the new European directive on vehicle recycling, vehicles manufactured after the 1st July 2003 should not contain any lead based products.</para><para translate="yes">Furthermore, with regard to bodywork repairs, these vehicles should not be repaired using tin, which contains a large amount of lead.</para><para translate="yes">The replacement solution for this type of operation is to use dual component polyester mastic containing aluminium. Aluminium panels are shape finished using "special aluminium" polyester mastic.</para><para translate="yes">It is important that the thickness of the residual mastic following sanding does not exceed<technicalvalue translate="no"><value translate="yes">1 mm</value></technicalvalue>.</para><descsection translate="no"><figure id="00-03-04-16-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-1" translate="no"><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000018304_LAY-000077047.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-03-04-16-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-1-000018304</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">Polyester mastic is applied using a block or broad knife.</para></descsection><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-8-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-7" translate="no"><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000027798_LAY-000077053.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-8-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-7-000027798</illusnum></figure><para translate="yes">Sanding during shaping should be done using<technicalvalue translate="no"><value translate="yes">P100</value></technicalvalue>dry sand paper with a large "file" type block.</para><para translate="yes">Surface finishing should be via light sanding using<technicalvalue translate="no"><value translate="yes">P150</value></technicalvalue>sand paper.</para><para translate="yes">Never use an "orbital" sander to sand during shape finishing, as the motion of this type of equipment is not suitable for the operation.</para></descsection></descbody></description></description></description><description id="d1e319" translate="no"><title translate="yes">removing dents from aluminium components</title><description id="d1e323" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Tools</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">The basic tools used are the same as for repairing steel panels.</para><para translate="yes">Only use tools and abrasive discs specifically used for repairing aluminium, in order to prevent contamination of the aluminium surface with steel particles, which could result in galvanic corrosion.</para><para translate="yes">Favour the use of mallets, wooden stakes or possibly plastic stakes.</para><para translate="yes">In order to prevent any impact marks and scratches, the metal tools should not have any sharp edges, and their surfaces should be smooth and polished.</para><para translate="yes">Consequently, finishing hammers (grooved face) must not be used.</para><para translate="yes">The edges of the files for soft metals should be rounded.</para></descbody></description><description id="d1e339" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Dent removal</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">There is a higher risk of lengthening aluminium panels than steel panels; for this reason, the planishing operation should be carried out gently.</para><para translate="yes">Panel lengthening can be eliminated by supplying heat (<technicalvalue translate="no"><value translate="yes">150˚C</value></technicalvalue>) which can be controlled using a temperature indicator.</para><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">Use a 150˚ Heat Marker to control the heating temperature correctly (see IXELL product catalogue ).</para></noteR></descbody></description><description id="d1e360" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Dent removal</title><descbody translate="no"><?Pub Dtl?><para translate="yes">Before heating, remove any sign of coating (paint, primer, cataphoretic coating), as these can affect the temperature reading.</para><para translate="yes">The flame of the blowtorch should be adjusted so that there is slightly more acetylene in relation to oxygen.</para><para translate="yes">Mark the area using the pencil.</para><descsection translate="no"><figure id="40-01-43-3-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-9" translate="no"><title translate="yes">checking the temperature</title><image dimension="F2 (85x85) #" href="../MergedPictures/ILL-000027793_LAY-000077055.png" style="width: 85.0mm; height: 85.0mm;" translate="no"/><illusnum>RDE-000316390-01-43-3-repair-40-01-43-02-21-1-1-9-000027793</illusnum><?Pub Caret -1?></figure></descsection><para translate="yes">The marks will melt when the temperature is reached.</para></descbody></description><description id="d1e381" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Finishing</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">                <sieref href="x-wc://gie=OR:wt.part.WTPartMaster:3475350"><linkdesc>aluminium bodywork component : preparation and paint range</linkdesc><linkvalue>GIEMR-002338</linkvalue></sieref>(94A, Paint application range for panels).</para></descbody></description></description><description id="d1e389" translate="no"><title translate="yes">JACKING</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">For reasons of passive safety, all jacking and straightening operations for structural components which have undergone deformation beyond the elastic limit (marked crumpling) must be followed by a planishing operation.</para><para translate="yes">This applies to all structural components, irrespective of the type of panel. They must be replaced if they cannot be straightened cold.</para><para translate="yes">It is very difficult to cold straighten an ultra high elastic limit panel, and you are strongly advised not to heat the material to make it malleable.</para><para translate="yes">For major impacts, it may be necessary to perform preliminary jacking in order to:</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">detach the electrical wiring harnesses,</li><li translate="yes">release the mechanical components to be removed,</li><li translate="yes">gain access to a joint.</li></ul><para translate="yes">This should not affect the choice of jacking equipment; this is made according to the type of repair to be carried out (see below).</para></descbody></description><description id="d1e411" translate="no"><title translate="yes">light jacking</title><description id="d1e415" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Jacking parts of a vehicle which do not have a direct influence on structural behaviour (e.g.: rear end panel, wheel arch, floor, linings)</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">All the straightening techniques described above may be used for any parts which are not directly visible and whose primary function is not structural.</para></descbody></description><description id="d1e421" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Jacking and straightening a structural component</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">For all straightening operations on one of these components, perfectly align the "edges" and blanks by "planishing" with a suitable stake and hammer.</para><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">Never use an inertia type straightening device.</para></noteR><para translate="yes">To do this, detach the component's closure panel to gain access to the internal face during straightening.</para><para translate="yes">You are strongly advised not to use shape finishing mastic on a structural component to hide residual crumpling.</para></descbody><description id="d1e442" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Jacking without subframe checks</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">When there is no need for geometry checks (e.g.: rear end panel, scuttle side panel upper reinforcement, front or rear side member ends), repair without parts replacement is carried out on a standard small straightening bench (See:<technicalvalue translate="no"><value translate="yes">Garage equipment catalogue</value></technicalvalue>).</para></descbody></description><description id="d1e453" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Jacking with subframe checks</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">When geometry checks are necessary (e.g.: assembled side members, front half unit or all parts comprising mechanical mounting points), repair without parts replacement is carried out on a small straightening bench equipped with special raised anchoring clamps to allow a geometry checking system to be positioned underneath the vehicle.</para></descbody></description></description></description><description id="d1e459" translate="no"><title translate="yes">heavy jacking and rebuilding with subframe checks</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">The parts concerned by this procedure are identified in each vehicle MR in sub-section 40A.</para><para translate="yes">The parts may be partially replaced, except for ultra high elastic limit components, for which complete replacement is compulsory.</para><para translate="yes">When straightening or replacing these parts, it is essential to check the geometry of the components; repairs are carried out on a repair bench (body jig bench) (See:<technicalvalue translate="no"><value translate="yes">Garage equipment catalogue</value></technicalvalue>.</para><para translate="yes">The repair bench consists of several components, each of which fulfils a distinct function:</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">The body jig bench : rigid base plate which simultaneously supports and secures the vehicle. This is equipped with an anchoring system comprising four anchoring clamps which may be fitted with additional retaining devices for the three-dimensional checks.</li><li translate="yes">The jacking system : must comprise at least a 10 tonne bracket, a special “pulling” chain and a gripping device.</li><li translate="yes">The geometry checking system : this may be either positive, or use three-dimensional measuring. It is used to check and realign important structural points during straightening operations, and the spatial positioning of replaced components in relation to the body.</li></ul></descbody></description></description>