<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2018, v.4002--><description xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" appl="X06/BVM5|X07/BVM5|X24/BVM6|X33/BVM5|X35/BVM5|X38/APL03/BVM6|X38/BVM5,BVM6|X41/BVM5|X44/BVM5|X45/BVM6|X52/BVM5,BVM6,BVR6,BVR5|X61/BVM5,BVM6|X62/BVM6,BVR6|X64/BVM5|X65/BVM5,BVM6|X66/BVM5,BVM6|X67/BVM5,BVM6|X70/BVM5,BVM6|X73/BVM6|X74/BVM5,BVM6|X76/APL03/BVM5|X77/BVM5,BVM6|X79/BVM5,BVM6,BVR6|X81/BVM6|X82/BVM6|X83/APL03/BVM5,BVM6|X84/BVM5,BVM6|X85/BVM5,BVM6|X87/BVM5,BVM6|X90/BVM5|X91/BVM6|X92/BVM5,BVM6,BVR6|X95/BVM5,BVM6|X98/BVM5|XFB/BVM5,BVM6|XFD/BVM6|XFE/BVM6|XHA/BVM5,BVM6|X40/BVM/5VIT|X43/BVM6|X54/BVM/5VIT|X56/BVM5|X57/BVM/5VIT|X63/BVM/5VIT|X94/BVM5|XZG/BVM6|XFA/BVM6|XFF/BVM5,BVM6|X55/BVM6|XJD/BVM5,BVM6|XZH/BVM6|XJA/BVM5,BVM6|XBB/BVM5|XJB/BVM5,BVM6|XJC/BVM5|XJE/BVM6|XJH/BVM6|XJK/BVM5,BVM6|XHA/H5H/FK0|X79/H5H/FK0|XBC/BVM5|XFK/BVM6|XJF/BVM5,BVM6|XHN/TL4|XFC/BVM6|XDD/PF6|XDE/PF6|X1310/BVM6|XDD/ZT5|XDE/ZT5|X82/ZT5" id="RDE-000171979" xml:lang="en" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="urn:ptc:names:renault:dita:xsd:description.xsd"><title translate="no">gearbox assembly: precautions for the repair</title><descprolog translate="no"><status name="Translated" translate="no"/><critdates translate="no"><created date="04/12/24 14:01" translate="no"/><revised modified="04/12/24 16:30" translate="no"/></critdates><descmetadata translate="no"><siename translate="no">gearbox assembly: precautions for the repair</siename><sieversion translate="no">Y.3</sieversion><sietype translate="yes">Description</sietype><sienumber translate="no">RDE-000171979</sienumber><domain translate="no">MR</domain><company translate="no">RENAULT</company></descmetadata></descprolog><descbody translate="no"><introduction translate="no"><para id="par10" translate="yes">All information contained in these manuals is intended exclusively for automotive industry professionals.</para><para id="par11" translate="yes">Since this documentation is intended to cover the whole range, throughout the world, it does not include equipment designed for use in specific countries.</para><para id="par12" translate="yes">The procedures and fault finding procedures recommended and described in this manual have been designed by automotive industry repair professionals.</para><noteR translate="no" type="warning"><para translate="yes">Before carrying out any operation on a vehicle fitted with the Stop &amp; Start system, always follow the safety instructions<sieref href="x-wc://gie=OR:wt.part.WTPartMaster:3503040"><linkdesc>vehicle: precautions for the repair</linkdesc><linkvalue>GIEMR-002446</linkvalue></sieref>  </para></noteR></introduction></descbody><description id="d1e215" translate="no" xml:lang="fr"><title translate="yes">General information</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">This method provides information which will allow you to:</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">acquire proper understanding of the component on which you will be working,</li><li translate="yes">benefit from the best conditions in which to carry out the repair,</li><li translate="yes">ensure that the component operates as well as possible, meeting customer requirements</li><li translate="yes">optimise component repair time</li><li translate="yes">work in the best safety conditions.</li></ul><para translate="yes">Please take the time to read this procedure as it will help you to save time when carrying out repairs.</para></descbody></description><description id="des4" translate="no"><title translate="yes">General recommendations</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">Observe the basic principles concerning vehicle repairs</para><para translate="yes">The quality of the repair depends first and foremost on how much care is exercised by the person carrying out the repair.</para><para translate="yes">Carry out the operation on the component in a clean working area.</para><para translate="yes">To ensure good repair: </para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">use the recommended consumables <sieref href="x-wc://gie=OR:wt.part.WTPartMaster:3542379"><linkdesc>vehicle: parts and consumables for the repair</linkdesc><linkvalue>GIEMR-002445</linkvalue></sieref>,</li><li translate="yes">use the recommended tools,</li><li translate="yes">observe the tightening torques,</li><li translate="yes">observe the recommendations for parts that should always be replaced after removal</li><li translate="yes">clean and degrease the areas to be bonded, to ensure they bond correctly</li></ul><noteR translate="no" type="caution"><para translate="yes">To ensure proper sealing, the joint faces must be clean, dry and free from greas (avoid any fingerprints)</para></noteR><noteR translate="no" type="caution"><para translate="yes">Do not scrape the joint faces of the aluminium: any damage caused to the joint face increases the risk of leaking.</para></noteR><para translate="yes">Use professional products and apply them with care (e.g. do not apply excessive sealing paste to the sealing surface, in order to prevent damage to the component).</para><noteR translate="no" type="caution"><para translate="yes">Applying excess sealant could cause it to be squeezed out when parts are tightened. Mixing sealant and fluid may cause damage to some components.</para></noteR><para translate="yes">Observe the chronological order of the steps:</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">remove the component,</li><li translate="yes">clean the component before repairing,</li><li translate="yes">remove the part(s) concerned</li><li translate="yes">check the part(s) removed,</li><li translate="yes">replace the faulty part(s) with new part(s),</li><li translate="yes">perform the necessary adjustments and/or calibrations so that the component operates correctly,</li><li translate="yes">observe the tightening torques.</li></ul><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">To prevent any contamination of components and to ensure the quality of the repair, it is strictly forbidden to re-use drained gearbox oil.</para></noteR><noteR translate="no" type="note"><para translate="yes">Note:</para><para translate="yes">Ensure that the parts removed match and ensure that they are refitted in the correct order.</para></noteR></descbody></description><description id="des3" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Special tooling</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">Use suitable tools which are in good condition (avoid the use of multi-purpose tools such as adjustable pliers).</para><para translate="yes">To ensure the good quality of repairs and safe working conditions, use only special tooling.</para></descbody></description><description id="des2" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Safety</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">Certain devices and parts must be handled with particular attention to safety and cleanliness and, above all, with due care.</para><para translate="yes">The safety symbol used in this manual indicates that special attention must be paid to the procedure or the tightening torque values.</para><para translate="yes">Working safely:</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">use personal protection (gloves, goggles, work shoes, masks, skin protection, etc.),</li><li translate="yes">check that the working area is clean and tidy during the operation,</li><li translate="yes">use supports and adopt a correct posture when performing heavy work or raising loads,</li><li translate="yes">use suitable tools which are in good condition (use of multi-purpose tools such as adjustable pliers etc. should be avoided).</li><li translate="yes">Do not put yourself in danger by hurrying or taking risks,</li><li translate="yes">do not use harmful products in unventilated rooms,</li><li translate="yes">always follow the safety instructions associated with the operation to be performed,</li><li translate="yes">do not ingest any chemicals (brake fluid, coolant, etc.).</li><li translate="yes">do not smoke when working on vehicles,</li></ul><para translate="yes">Respecting the environment:</para><ul translate="no"><li translate="yes">sort waste according to its particular qualities,</li><li translate="yes">do not burn discarded products (tyres, etc.).</li></ul></descbody></description><?Pub Caret -1?><description id="des1" translate="no"><title translate="yes">Conclusion</title><descbody translate="no"><para translate="yes">Respecting the recommended methods will guarantee the best performance and reliability of the component.</para></descbody></description></description>